{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The namesake ship of the Mataafa storm was wrecked in this body of water in 1905. Large cobblestone pits built by a pre-Ojibwa people around this body of water are named after a river that flows into it, the Pukaskwa. All 29 crewmembers were killed in a shipwreck on this lake involving a freighter carrying iron ore. Thunder Bay is the largest city that lies along this lake, which also contains Duluth, Minnesota. The SS Edmund Fitzgerald sank in, for ten points, what largest of the Great Lakes?",
      "answer": "Lake Superior"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s actions sparked Donatist opposition to the “traditors.” This leader solidified his rule by defeating Carinus at the Battle of the Margus. Causanius led a revolt in Britannia during this ruler’s reign, causing Maximian to be elevated to Augustus. This man was the first Roman emperor to abdicate, retiring to his palace at Split. For ten points, name this emperor who organized the Tetrarchy and conducted the last Christian persecutions.",
      "answer": "Diocletian or Gaius Aurelius Valerius Diocletianus Augustus, but do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man replaced John Carver as governor, and his successor Edward Winslow co-wrote Mourt’s Relation with him. During this man’s leadership, the Nemasket Raid was launched by Myles Standish. Samoset contacted the English during this man’s leadership, thus establishing relations with Massasoit. This Puritan leader documented the landing at Cape Cod and his signing of the Mayflower Compact. For ten points, name this five-time governor of Plymouth Colony and author of On Plymouth Plantation.",
      "answer": "William Bradford"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1639, Queen Christina of Sweden invited this thinker to organize an academy of science and to tutor her. One of his major works is presented as the product of six days thinking in solitude. This thinker argued that the soul was in the pineal gland as part of his theory of mind-body dualism, which he explored in part of his Meditations on First Philosophy. For ten points, name this philosopher whose Discourse on Method includes the concept “I think, therefore I am.”",
      "answer": "Ren´e Descartes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle’s winners opened fire on William Stevenson’s friendly unit when it insisted on retreating to Helpmekaar. Members of John Chard’s engineers were caught in this battle after they were dispatched to repair pontoon bridges on the Buffalo River. Eleven Victoria Crosses were awarded for this battle, the most ever given to a single regiment. This battle’s winners defended a hospital building on the same day that the Battle of Isandlwana was fought. For ten points, name this 1879 battle in which 100 British troops repelled a Zulu impi.",
      "answer": "Battle of Rorke’s Drift"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Roberts noted that in this ruling, “it’s quite clear that [the Supreme Court isn’t] interpreting the law, they’re making the law.” In one dissent during this case, Oliver Wendell Holmes’s dissent in this case noted “The Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer’s Social Statics.” West Coast Hotel Co. v. Parrish ended a forty-year era named for this case in which the Supreme Court consistently sided against economic regulation. For ten points, name this 1905 Supreme Court case that cited due process in overturning a law limiting the work hours of bakers in New York.",
      "answer": "Lochner v. New York"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one game in this series, the American government uses the Bay of Pigs invasion as an alibi for a cosmonaut’s injuries sustained during Project Mercury. The end of the Cuban Missile Crisis thwarts the attempted defection of Nikolai Sokolov in this series. The Outer Heaven mercenary company, owned by Ocelot, grows strong enough to challenge world governments in this series’ fourth installment, “The Guns of the Patriots.” Hideo Kojima created, for ten points, what iconic stealth video game franchise whose protagonist is Solid Snake?",
      "answer": "Metal Gear"
    },
    {
      "question": "This right was encouraged by a movement founded by Elizabeth Vesey and Elizabeth Montagu, the Blue Stockings Society. A report by Charles Talleyrand claimed women should only have limited access to this right; a response to that report noted that women only appeared irrational because they were denied this right, which is necessary for women to properly raise their children. Mary Wollstonecraft argued for women’s access to, for ten points, what right, the subject of Jean-Jacques Rousseau’s Emile [ay-meel]?",
      "answer": [
        "education",
        "equivalent answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Nazi playwright Dietrich Eckart’s racist adaptation of this play depicts the Great Boyg and the Green-Clad Woman as Jews who are shamed and outsmarted by the title, Germanic character. In this play, Helga receives a silver button as a gift to her sister, Solveig, This play’s incidental music, including the songs “Morning Mood” and “The Death of Ase” was written by Edvard Grieg. For ten points, name this play written by Henrik Ibsen about a title Norwegian hero.",
      "answer": "Peer Gynt"
    },
    {
      "question": "This kingdom was forced to cede sovereignty to Great Britain by the captain George Paulet. A ruler of this kingdom was aided by Gerrit Judd and proclaimed the Great Mahele [ma-hay-lay] to redistribute land. The unifier of this kingdom protected noncombatants by proclaiming the Law of the Splintered Paddle. A queen of this kingdom was forced to agree to the Bayonet Constitution by American forces. For ten points, name this Pacific kingdom ruled by Kamehameha [ka-MAY-ha-MAY-ha] and Lili’uokalani [LILY-oh-ka-LAH-nee].",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Hawai’i"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The city of Konigsberg was named in honor of a ruler from this region, Ottokar II, who led this region to complete defeat at the hands of Rudolf I at the Battle on the Marchfeld. This region’s Premyslid dynasty was replaced by the House of Luxembourg in 1306. The execution of a preacher at the Council of Constance led to the namesake Hussite Wars in this region. For ten points, name this central European region that makes up most of the Czech Republic.",
        "answer": "Bohemia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The last Premyslid ruler of Bohemia was the third king of this name. This name is shared by the patron saint of Bohemia and an important public square in Prague.",
        "answer": [
          "Wenceslas",
          "Wenceslaus III",
          "Saint Wenceslas",
          "Wenceslas Square"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s most famous creation was spawned with the help of Henry Senger and Warren Olney. This man’s theories on valley formation were backed up by the discovery of an alpine glacier below Merced Peak and a later “noble earthquake” at Lone Pine. This man, who broke with Gifford Pinchot over sheep grazing and the damming of a California valley, was photographed with Teddy Roosevelt atop Glacier Point, part of the Yosemite National Park he helped preserve. For ten points, name this Scottish-American naturalist who founded the Sierra Club.",
        "answer": "John Muir"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Muir opposed the construction of the O’Shaughnessy Dam, which eventually turned this valley into a reservoir on the Tuolumne River within Yosemite National Park.",
        "answer": [
          "Hetch Hetchy Valley",
          "Hetch Hetchy Reservoir"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This body’s topography is divided into 30 quadrangles. In 1877, Giovanni Schiaparelli [skap-uh-relli] claimed that canals existed on this body, which was explored by the Viking program. NASA’s Mariner mission discovered the largest known volcano in the solar system, Mons Olympus, on this planet. Opportunity and Spirit explored the surface of, for ten points, what “red” planet, the fourth from the Sun?",
        "answer": "Mars"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The theory that canals of liquid water existed on Mars was disproven by space missions, but was doubted far earlier through the use of this method of analyzing wavelengths of emitted radiation in the Martian atmosphere.",
        "answer": [
          "emission spectroscopy",
          "word forms like spectroscopic analysis"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader once gave a conciliatory speech in English before switching to his native language to say “we will crush them.” This leader launched a guerrilla war known as the Second Chimurenga, and he outmaneuvered Joshua Nkomo and Bishop Abel Muzorewa to assume control of his country. Ian Smith fought the Rhodesian Bush War against this man’s ZANU-PF party. For ten points, name this autocratic longtime President of Zimbabwe.",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2017, this ally of Mugabe succeeded him as President of Zimbabwe.",
        "answer": "Emmerson Mnangagwa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "RichardNixonofferedtoletoneofthisstate’ssenatorslistentoandsummarizetheWhiteHousetapes, probably because he was nearly deaf. In response to the Peekskill riots, John Rankin, a representative from this state, screamed racial slurs on the floor of the House of Representatives. Trent Lott and Thad Cochran resigned as senators from this state, which is currently represented by Roger Wicker and Cindy Hyde-Smith. For ten points, name this southern US state where, in 1964, governor Ross Barnett tried to refuse James Meredith’s enrollment at its state university?",
        "answer": "Mississippi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nixon planned to ask this senator from Mississippi to listen to the tapes. This man served in the Senate for over 41 years, and signed the Southern Manifesto opposing racial integration.",
        "answer": "John Stennis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the conclusion of one of this man’s works, a wheelchair-ridden Edgar Ray Killen appears to brag about the murders he committed as a member of the Klan; that opera alternates between the civil rights movement and the end of the Civil War and is called Appomattox. One of this man’s operas features the funeral of Amenhotep III and the “Hymn of the Sun,” and another includes a series of “knee plays.” For ten points, name this American composer whose Akhenaten is part of a trilogy with Einstein on the Beach.",
        "answer": "Philip Glass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Akhenaten and Einstein on the Beach are parts of Glass’s Portrait trilogy, as is this work about three nonviolent activists: Leo Tolstoy, Martin Luther King, and Mahatma Gandhi.",
        "answer": "Satyagraha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when the promise of treasure from a chevauchee and seven years of peace was rendered undesirable by one side, whose troops were advised by William Douglas to attack without horses. The Captal de Buch masterminded a victorious flanking maneuver in this battle, which featured fighting by a young Philip the Bold. The Treaty of Bretigny was signed after this battle and granted three million gold crowns to its winning side. Edward the Black Prince won, for ten points, what 1356 battle during the Hundred Years War in which King John II of France was taken hostage?",
        "answer": "Battle of Poitiers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Discontent over the French loss at Poitiers and high taxes led to this peasant uprising. The leader of this rebellion, Guillaume Cale, was beheaded by Charles the Bad before the Battle of Mello.",
        "answer": "Jacquerie"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1988, electoral fraud in this country was explained by the phrase “the system crashed,” which was later declared to be a lie by outgoing President Miguel de la Madrid. This country, whose ruling party was described as “the perfect dictatorship,” put down a revolt at the Plaza de Tres Culturas in the Tlatelolco neighborhood during the 1968 Summer Olympics. From 1929 to 2000, the PRI controlled the Presidency of, for ten points, what country that recently elected Andr´es Manuel L´opez Obrador?",
        "answer": "M´exico or the United Mexican States"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This party’s Manuel Clouthier finished 3rd in the controversial 1988 presidential elections, but in 2000, it became the first party to defeat a PRI-backed candidate when Vicente Fox took office.",
        "answer": [
          "PAN or Partido Acci´on Nacional",
          "National Action Party"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "William Rehnquist",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who nominated him as Associate Justice in 1971.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "1973 case concerning abortion in which Rehnquist was one of two dissenters.",
          "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action that was determined in Lee v. Weisman to be illegal if led by a school-sponsored rabbi, with Rehnquist dissenting.",
          "answer": "school prayer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action that was determined in Texas v. Johnson to be legal, with Rehnquist dissenting.",
          "answer": [
            "flag burning",
            "flag desecration"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2000 case in which Rehnquist’s court ended the Florida recount.",
          "answer": "Bush v. Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man he succeeded as Chief Justice in 1986.",
          "answer": "Warren Burger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attorney General under Bill Clinton who was the defendant in the 1993 Shaw redistricting case.",
          "answer": [
            "Janet Reno",
            "Shaw v Reno"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Justice who was appointed to the Supreme Court by FDR, who was Chief US Prosecutor at the Nuremberg Trials, and who Rehnquist clerked for.",
          "answer": "Robert H. Jackson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Poland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City that replaced Krakow in 1793 as the Polish capital and remains the capital today.",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion adopted by Mieszko I in 966 after a lengthy process of converting pagan tribes.",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Roman Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that, along with Austria and Russia, partitioned Poland in 1793.",
          "answer": "Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Polish nationals like Casimir Pulaski fought and died in Savannah.",
          "answer": "American Revolutionary War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottoman Sultan who declared war with Poland over Moldavia. An earlier sultan of the same name founded the Ottoman Empire.",
          "answer": "Osman I and/or II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty whose rule of Poland ended with Sigismund II’s successor Henry de Valois. It ruled Poland from 1386 to 1572.",
          "answer": "Jagiellonian Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought by Poland against Ivan the Terrible over a region relinquished by Russia in the Peace of Jam Zapolski.",
          "answer": "Livonian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish king during the Great Northern War who developed the city of Dresden and briefly abdicated the throne.",
          "answer": "Augustus the Strong or Augustus II"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mughal Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Mughal Empire, a descendant of Tamerlane.",
          "answer": "Babur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mausoleum built by Shah Jahan for his wife, Mumtaz.",
          "answer": "Taj Mahal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battlesite where, in 1526, that first emperor defeated Ibrahim Lodi, the last Sultan of Delhi.",
          "answer": "First Battle of Panipat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chair of the Mughal Emperors, which was carried off to Persia after Nader Shah’s sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "Peacock Throne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military building in Delhi built by the Mughals, named for its distinctive color.",
          "answer": "Red Fort"
        },
        {
          "question": "Syncretic faith founded by the third Mughal emperor in 1582.",
          "answer": "Din-i-Illahi"
        },
        {
          "question": "1739 victory for Nader Shah against the Mughal emperor Muhammad Shah that opened the way for his sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "Battle of Karnal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire led by Sher Shah that conquered much of Northern India during the reign of Humayun.",
          "answer": "Suri Empire"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s attempts to take the Saintonge were completely defeated at the Battle of Taillebourg. This man later forgave rebels who had captured him at the Battle of Lewes in his Dictum of Kenilworth, which only stipulated fines. After a (20 pts)",
        "papal bull exempted this man from the Provisions of Oxford, he was forced to fight the Second (10 pts)",
        "Baron’s War, eventually winning at the Battle of Evesham. For ten points, name this Plantagenet king who feuded with Louis IX and Simon de Montfort, was succeeded by Edward I, and ruled England in the 13th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry III or Henry of Winchester"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this event, the residents of New York gave a small gold box as a token of gratitude to one of its participants. James DeLancey’s appointment as colonial Chief Justice after the firing of Lewis Morris was a central cause of this event, which began with a (20 pts)",
        "sharp criticism of William Cosby. Andrew Hamilton represented this event’s central figure, who (10 pts)",
        "published the New York Weekly Journal. Truth was upheld as a defense against libel in, for ten points, what 1735 case against a German-American journalist, an early American victory for freedom of the press?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "libel trial of John Peter Zenger",
        "descriptions thereof"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Schools called Nizamiyyah were established in this empire, whose rulers sought guidance from a vizier’s manual, the “Book of Government.” This empire’s founder, Tughril, won the Battle of Dandanaqan over the (20 pts)",
        "Ghaznavids. An entity administered by this empire was rivaled by the Danishmends and lost to the Mongols at the Battle of Kose Dag. That offshoot of this empire, the (10 pts)",
        "Sultanate of Rum, was created after Byzantine Emperor Romanos IV was captured at the Battle of Manzikert. Malik Shah I and Alp Arslan once ruled, for ten points, what empire that was founded in 1037 and based in Anatolia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Seljuk Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region was the target of Operation Chastise, where the so-called “Dambuster” bouncing torpedo bombs struck the Mohne and Edersee dams to cause massive flooding. A namesake International Authority attempting to wrest control of this region was abandoned after (20 pts)",
        "Konrad Adenauer agreed to put its resources under the European Coal and Steel Community. Along with the (10 pts)",
        "Saarland, French troops were deployed in this region until reparations could be repaid at the end of World War I. Gelsenkirchen and Dortmund are cities of, for ten points, what steel producing valley of Germany?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ruhr Valley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this dynasty came to power after defeated his brother Sviatopolk and passed a law code called the Russkaya Pravda. Another ruler of this dynasty converted to (20 pts)",
        "Christianity when he learned about the Islamic prohibition on alcohol and led a 988 mass baptism of his kingdom. The founding of this dynasty was described in the Primary Chronicle. This dynasty ended after (10 pts)",
        "Feodor I was succeeded by Michael Romanov in 1613. For ten points name this dynasty that ruled the Kievan Rus, and later Russia, until the Time of Troubles."
      ],
      "answer": "Rurikid Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After his patron refused to pay him for one work, this artist painted Frederick Leyland as an anthropomorphic bird playing a piano. This artist of The Gold Scab was bankrupted when he received just a quarter-penny in an 1877 libel suit against John (20 pts)",
        "Ruskin, who claimed he was “flinging a pot of paint in the public’s face” with his (10 pts)",
        "Nocturne in Black and Gold: The Falling Rocket. A seated woman in a black dress is the subject of an “Arrangement” by, for ten points, what artist, who had his mother sit for the painting?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Abbott McNeill Whistler"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Dorman Bridgman Eaton wrote this bill, whose namesake, the vice-presidential candidate on George McClellan’s losing ticket in the 1864 election, served with John Sherman as senators from Ohio. (20 pts)",
        "Roscoe Conkling and other members of the Stalwart faction opposed this piece of legislation, which was prompted after an event at the Baltimore & Potomac (10 pts)",
        "Railroad Station in 1881. Charles Guiteau’s assassination of James Garfield prompted the passage of, for ten points, what bill that reformed the spoils system within American civil service?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act or Bill,",
        "Law"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One work by this author is structured as a Socratic dialogue among his discussion group, the Orti Oricellari, and criticizes condottieri mercenaries. After a defeat at Prato for the citizen militia founded by this man, he followed (20 pts)",
        "Pietro Soderini into exile and wrote a work that is often accompanied by this man’s made-up biography of Castruccio Castracane. This man’s most famous work holds (10 pts)",
        "Cesare Borgia as an ideal ruler, stresses the idea of virtu´, and was dedicated to Lorenzo de Medici. For ten points, name this Florentine writer who held that it is better to be feared than loved in his The Prince."
      ],
      "answer": "Niccol´o Machiavelli"
    }
  ]
}